foreign
I'll share with you the skills that you
need to have to become a back-end python
developer I'm taking these skills from
my knowledge as well as doing some
research and looking at some recent job
postings relating to python positions so
that said let's get into the video after
a quick word from our sponsor before we
get started I need to thank lenode for
sponsoring this video I've been using
and working with lenode for nearly three
years now and they've consistently been
my go-to choice for hosting my
applications and servers in fact right
now I'm using the node to host the
official Tech with Tim Discord bot a
website multiple of my domains and a
kubernetes cluster now lenode was just
recently acquired by Akamai and as a
part of this acquisition they're going
to be adding more than a dozen new data
centers around the world in the next
year lenode makes it super easy to spin
up servers with their one-click app
Marketplace and have tons of written
guides and YouTube videos on their
channel to help you get started now if
you're having any issues you can reach
out to the 24 7 support team and
actually talk with a real human being
now the node's pricing is simple with no
hidden fees and full transparency and
you can test out the node services for
free by using the link in the
description and claiming in a hundred
dollar sixty day credit for any new
accounts it's been an absolute pleasure
to work with lenode over the past few
years and one last thank you to them for
sponsoring this video alright so let's
go ahead and dive in now I quickly want
to mention if you haven't already heard
I just released a brand new course it's
called blockchain expert if you're
looking to get into web 3 learn about
blockchain Technology's solidity web3
fundamentals Etc then check it out from
the link in the description I know you
guys will find some value but that said
though let's get into the skills
now obviously you can land a python
developer position without having
everything on this list but I think if
you want it to be considered for kind of
a like let's say mid-level or maybe even
a higher level position you would need
to have everything here that said I'm
sure you could join as kind of a junior
python developer or a junior back-end
developer and work your way up and learn
some of the missing skills if you didn't
have all of so the first thing you're
going to have to have here pretty
obvious is python skills you need to
understand python fundamentals I don't
think you need to be an expert in Python
you don't have to know everything about
like generators uh iterators uh meta
classes all of that kind of advanced
syntax but I would know for Loops
functions classes objects and a lot of
the common and core syntax and
functionality that you'd use on an
everyday basis
okay so moving on to the second skill
you would need to have to become a
back-end python developer this may seem
a little counter-intuitive but this is
some basic front-end skills now whenever
you're working on the back end you're
still going to be touching aspects of
the front end even if you're not writing
front end code you might have to
understand it digest it kind of look at
it and read it and for that reason you
should understand some basic HTML basic
CSS you should understand maybe a little
bit of JavaScript again you don't need
to be an expert or a master in this but
you need to have some fluency and the
ability to at least read some of that
code so I would spend a bit of time
maybe a week or two kind of looking into
some of those skills learning how to
build some basic front ends maybe you
want to dabble in something like react
view angular some other popular
Frameworks that's up to you but I would
know some basic front-end skills
now beyond that knowledge the next thing
that you would need to know to become a
back-end python developer is some basic
networking skills now I think you could
probably get away without having this
but I would highly recommend spending a
few days learning about basic networking
so learning about HTTP what is that
protocol how does that work how do you
serve data over the web learning about
IP addresses learning about say
firewalls learning about vpns and just
again kind of fundamental things related
to networking maybe you want to learn
why localhost works the way it does
about different ports about you know
kind of standard ports you'd have for a
website versus ports for other services
again just some fundamental knowledge in
this area I think will go a long way so
I would learn about basic Networks
now moving beyond networking the next
thing I would learn is related to Linux
and also I'll clarify here I wouldn't
learn these necessarily in any
particular order I think the order I
have is actually decent but just
throwing it out there you can kind of
learn this in any order so let me take
that back the next thing just something
I would learn would be Linux now you
want to learn about how to operate in a
Linux environment so what different
Linux users are Linux permissions Linux
commands how do you copy paste move
files around you want to be comfortable
working on just strictly the command
line and not relying on a graphical user
interface now I actually have an entire
Linux tutorial series that's designed
specifically for programmers looking to
kind of learn this basic knowledge so
I'll link that in the description in
case you're curious it is completely
free
right
so next after learning Linux I would
start learning Django and flask which
are web Frameworks that utilize now
these are great to learn regardless if
you want to be a python backend
developer but I think if you want to be
a backend developer you're going to have
to be competent with these Frameworks
and learn more than just the basics you
want to learn kind of the intermediate
and advanced topics within this and be
very comfortable writing code in Django
and flask now flask is the more basic of
these two Frameworks so I would start by
learning that understand how to create a
website with it how to create an API
with it how to do security
authentication logging in logging out
you may even want to look at websockets
using flask that could be a cool project
next though you want to get into Django
now Django is a lot more complicated it
has many more tools and features but
it's used by large companies like
Instagram Spotify Mozilla National
Geographic and a bunch of other ones as
well so just learning Django will open
you up to a lot of job opportunities but
again you want to be learning about
authentication page routing how to do
apis more Advanced features Django
extensions databases specifically
databases and learning the kind of
database model within Django that's a
bit complicated but something you
definitely need to learn if you want to
be a back-end python developer
now Beyond Django the next thing that I
would start looking into is API design
and just apis in general learning about
kind of how those work the different
routes you can set up crud apis more
complex apis and specifically related to
kind of permissions and authentications
around that personally I always find
that the most complicated stuff is doing
authentication specifically token
authentication or other aspects of
authentication where you have a refresh
token an expiry date you have maybe
username password authentication there's
a lot of different ways to do this and
it's going to change depending on the
framework that you're using so I would
be really really comfortable creating
apis designing apis working with
Frameworks like Django and flask maybe
even fast API and just be comfortable
doing this almost know how to do it kind
of off the top of your head to spin up a
quick API add some authorization or
authentication understand what JWT
tokens are and all the other stuff that
you're going to be using frequently if
you're a back-end developer now beyond
that I would also look at stuff like
rate limiting how you host your apis how
you make make sure your apis are secure
and not being hit by too many people
there's all kinds of stuff to look at in
this and I'm no expert in this field but
those are some of the things I would
start really kind of researching if I
was thinking about becoming a more
full-time python back-end development
so next we move on to probably my least
favorite topic but this is databases now
the reality is if you want to be a
back-end developer of any kind you have
to understand databases this is a very
very important part of your job and you
need to know how to create databases
delete them migrate them do maintenance
on them add new tables add relationships
do database design how to host databases
how to protect and secure your databases
there is so much stuff relating to data
how to back up your databases how to
part put part of your database in
another database and access it from
somewhere else there is so much stuff
related to this and that's going to come
with learning SQL now there's a lot of
companies now that are using nosql
databases for example my startup
velocity uses a nosql database which is
Firebase however
um you know it's probably a good idea to
understand SQL and I myself took I think
two SQL courses in University sorry for
the cut there you can see my cap behind
me was about to be stopping my recording
so I had to step in there and fix that
but as I was saying you need to learn
SQL you need to understand how to
structure databases create them query
them run SQL commands and I would also
be familiar with nosql databases and
understand a little bit about how to
structure your data in a nosql database
because that's different than working
with a SQL database with a nosql
database you're fairly Limited in terms
of query operations due to the limited
structure that's imposed so the way you
structure your data is much different
and you end up having a lot of redundant
data that's actually kind of part of the
design process of working with a nosql
database anyways look into that you're
going to have to understand SQL I would
kind of focus there and then maybe just
learn a bit about nosql to kind of have
some experience with that in case a job
required
so last thing on my list here is
something that really should be its own
job and with a lot of companies it is
however if you're working maybe for a
smaller company or I don't know some
companies just require this you have to
have devops skills now this really means
your experience working with the cloud
you understand how to deploy how to host
specific things how to go in there and
maybe change something do some
maintenance uh you should have
experience working in a cloud
environment like AWS Azure Google Cloud
whatever it is this company uses usually
they require some experience in that
specific environment now again I really
feel like this is its own job there is
so much stuff to learn related to devops
and I mean this could be a whole video
on its own how to be a devops engineer
which I'm not even really qualified to
talk about the reality is that a lot of
companies are requiring this right so I
think having a little bit of experience
with this being able to not look like
you don't have any experience is
probably what you're going for in this
category so yeah learn a little bit of
devops now I will lastly mention you
also of course want to learn Git Version
Control GitHub I think that goes without
saying so I didn't really mention it too
explicitly but I would definitely learn
that and that's pretty much a
requirement for any programming job so
that's it guys I'm going to start
wrapping it up here make sure to check
out blockchain expert from the link in
the description if you're interested in
web3 or blockchain Technologies and you
want to become a blockchain engineer
with that said I will see you in another
YouTube video
[Music]
thank you